The recent debate over copyright laws
إن النقاش الدائر مؤخراً حول قوانين حقوق الملكية الفكرية
like SOPA in the United States
مثل قانون وقف القرصنة على الانترنت فى الولايات المتحدة
and the ACTA agreement in Europe
واتفاقية التجارة لمكافحة التزوير فى أوروبا
has been very emotional.
أصبح حساساً للغاية
And I think some dispassionate, quantitative reasoning
واعتقد أن بعض الهدوء والمنطق الكمي
could really bring a great deal to the debate.
قد يجعلنا نصل جدياً لاتفاق عظيم في هذا النقاش
I'd therefore like to propose
.لذلك أحب أن اوضح
that we employ, we enlist,
إننا نوظف ونحشد
the cutting edge field of copyright math
آخر ما توصلنا له في حسابات حقوق الطبع والنشر
whenever we approach this subject.
كلما تطرقنا إلى هذا الموضوع .
For instance, just recently
على سبيل المثال
the Motion Picture Association revealed
ً أظهرت نقابة الأفلام السينيمائية مؤخرا
that our economy loses 58 billion dollars a year
أن إقتصادنا يخسر حوالي 58 بليون دولار سنوياً
to copyright theft.
بسبب سرقات حقوق الملكية الفكرية
Now rather than just argue about this number,
والآن بدلاً من فقط النقاش حول هذا الرقم
a copyright mathematician will analyze it
, سوف يقوم متخصص رياضيات بتحليل ذلك
and he'll soon discover that this money
وسوف يكتشف إن هذه الاموال
could stretch from this auditorium
من الممكن أن تتمدد من هذا المسرح
all the way across Ocean Boulevard
على الطريق عبر "شارع المحيط"
to the Westin, and then to Mars ...
إلى "ويستن" ومنه إلى كوكب المريخ
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
... if we use pennies.
لو كنا نستخدم البنسات
Now this is obviously a powerful,
والآن يبدو بوضوح أنه أمر هام
some might say dangerously powerful, insight.
وبنظرة متأنية تبدو خطورة أهميته .
But it's also a morally important one.
ولكنه أيضاً له أهمية أخلاقيه
Because this isn't just the hypothetical retail value
فهو ليس مجرد قيمة افتراضية
of some pirated movies that we're talking about,
لبيع الأفلام المقرصنة بالتجزئة
but this is actual economic losses.
لكنه يعد خسارة اقتصادية حقيقية
This is the equivalent
هذا يعادل
to the entire American corn crop failing
الخسارة الكاملة لمحصول الذرة الامريكي
along with all of our fruit crops,
بالاضافة لكل محاصيل الفاكهة
as well as wheat, tobacco,
وكذلك القمح والتبغ
rice, sorghum --
-والارز والسرغوم- الذرة البيضاء
whatever sorghum is -- losing sorghum.
أيا كان هذا السرغوم! فسوف نخسره كذلك
But identifying the actual losses to the economy
ولكن التعرف على الخسارة الحقيقية في الاقتصاد
is almost impossible to do
يبدو مستحيلاً
unless we use copyright math.
بدون حساب حقوق الملكية الفكرية
Now music revenues are down by about eight billion dollars a year
فايرادات الموسيقى الآن في هبوط بحوالي 8 بليون دولار في العام
since Napster first came on the scene.
منذ دخول شركة نابستر في المشهد
So that's a chunk of what we're looking for.
هذا جزء مما نبحث عنه
But total movie revenues
ولكن عائدات الافلام
across theaters, home video and pay-per-view are up.
سواء من المسارح أو الفيديو المنزلي أو صالات العرض تشهد صعوداً
And TV, satellite and cable revenues are way up.
كذلك عائدات التلفاز و الاقمار الصناعية والكابلات تشهد صعوداً
Other content markets like book publishing and radio
محتويات السوق الأخرى كنشر الكتب والاذاعة
are also up.
أيضاً في صعود
So this small missing chunk here
لذا هذه الحلقة الصغيرة المفقودة هنا
is puzzling.
تبدو محيرة .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Since the big content markets
منذ أن تنامى المحتوى الكبير للأسواق
have grown in line with historic norms,
بالتوافق مع المعايير التاريخية
it's not additional growth that piracy has prevented,
فإن القرصنة لم تمنع هذا النمو الاضافي
but copyright math tells us
لكن حساب حقوق النشر يخبرنا
it must therefore be foregone growth
انه لابد أن يكون هناك نمو حتمي
in a market that has no historic norms --
في السوق بدون معايير تاريخية
one that didn't exist in the 90's.
أي لم يكن موجوداً في التسعينيات
What we're looking at here
ما نبحث عنه هنا
is the insidious cost of ringtone piracy.
هو التكلفة الماكرة لقرصنة النغمات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
50 billion dollars of it a year,
50 بليون دولار في العام
which is enough, at 30 seconds a ringtone,
النغمة 30 ثانية
that could stretch from here
والذي يكفي لان يمتد من هنا
to Neanderthal times.
حتى العصر البدائي للبشرية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's true.
هذا حقيقي
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I have Excel.
لديّ برنامج اكسل
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The movie folks also tell us
يخبرنا أصحاب الأفلام أيضاً
that our economy loses
أن أقتصادنا يخسر
over 370,000 jobs to content theft,
أكثر من 370،000 وظيفة بسبب قرصنة المحتوى
which is quite a lot when you consider that, back in '98,
والذي يبدو كثيرا جدا عند الوضع في الاعتبار أنه في عام 1998
the Bureau of Labor Statistics indicated
أشار مكتب إحصاءات العمل
that the motion picture and video industries
أن صناعة الفيديو وأفلام السينما
were employing 270,000 people.
توظف حوالى 270،000 شخص
Other data has the music industry at about 45,000 people.
بينما صناعة الموسيقى حوالي 45،000 شخص
And so the job losses that came with the Internet
وتم خسارة هذه الوظائف بظهور الانترنت
and all that content theft,
وقرصنة المحتوى
have therefore left us with negative employment in our content industries.
وبذلك أصبح لدينا بطالة في صناعة المحتوى
And this is just one of the many mind-blowing statistics
وهذا فقط واحده من كثير من احصاءات
that copyright mathematicians have to deal with every day.
يتعامل معها علماء الرياضيات في حقوق النشر يومياً
And some people think that string theory is tough.
ويعتقد بعض الناس أن نظرية الأوتار الفائقة صعبة .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Now this is a key number from the copyright mathematicians' toolkit.
والآن هذا هو رقم مهم من مجموعة أدوات رياضيي حقوق النشر
It's the precise amount of harm
هذه هي الكمية الدقيقة للضرر
that comes to media companies
الذي يصيب شركات الاعلام
whenever a single copyrighted song or movie
كلما تم قرصنة فيلم أو أغنية
gets pirated.
محفوظة الحقوق
Hollywood and Congress derived this number mathematically
هوليوود والكونغرس استنتجوا هذا الرقم رياضياً
back when they last sat down to improve copyright damages
مرة أخرى عندما اجتمعا مؤخراً للعمل على تحسين الأضرار التي تصيب حقوق النشر
and made this law.
وتقديم هذا القانون
Some people think this number's a little bit large,
يعتقد بعض الناس أن هذا الرقم كبير نوعا ما
but copyright mathematicians who are media lobby experts
لكن رياضيي حقوق النشر الذين هم خبراء باللوبي الاعلامي
are merely surprised
متفاجئين تماما
that it doesn't get compounded for inflation every year.
لأن الامور لم تتفاقم برغم ارتفاع معدلات التضخم كل عام
Now when this law first passed,
عندما تم تطبيق هذا القانون لأول مرة
the world's hottest MP3 player could hold just 10 songs.
أصبح أقوى مشغل موسيقي في العالم لا يمكنه تخزين أكثر من عشر أغنيات
And it was a big Christmas hit.
وهذه كانت أقوى ضربة في عيد الميلاد
Because what little hoodlum wouldn't want
لأنه ما من قرصان صغير يريد
a million and a half bucks-worth of stolen goods in his pocket.
أن يحمل في جيبه من البضائع المسروقة ما قيمته مليون ونصف دولار
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
These days an iPod Classic can hold 40,000 songs,
في هذه الايام يسع الآي بود الكلاسيك حوالى 40،000 أغنية
which is to say eight billion dollars-worth
أي ما يعادل 8 بليون دولار
of stolen media.
من الميديا المسروقة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Or about 75,000 jobs.
أو حوالي 75،000 وظيفة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now you might find copyright math strange,
قد تبدو حسابات حقوق النشر غريبة الآن
but that's because it's a field
ولكن لأن هذا المجال
that's best left to experts.
هو أفضل ما تبقى للخبراء
So that's it for now.
هذا هو الأمر في الوقت الراهن
I hope you'll join me next time
أتمنى أن تشاركوني المرة القادمة
when I will be making an equally scientific and fact-based inquiry
عندما أقوم ببحثي العلمي المبني على حقائق
into the cost of alien music piracy to he American economy.
عن تكلفة قرصنة موسيقى الكائنات الفضائية وتأثيرها على الاقتصاد الأمريكي
Thank you very much.
شكراٌ جزيلاٌ لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم